Guide to the Solon De Leon Papers TAM.092
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Solon De Leon Papers
1900-1980
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
De Leon, Solon, 1883-
Gottesman, Ruth De Leon
TAM.092
2 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons
Solon De Leon, son of Daniel De Leon, Marxist theoretician and leader of the Socialist Labor Party, was a socialist, labor educator and labor journalist. The collection contains correspondence with his father and other SLP leaders, unpublished writings, clippings, and memorabilia.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Ruth De Leon Gottesman in 1977; an additional accession was donated in 2013. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 1977.003 and 2015.012.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Solon De Leon was born in New York City on September 2, 1883. He was the son of Daniel De Leon, Marxist theoretician and leader of the Socialist Labor Party (SLP). Although his parents were Jewish, he was unaware of this until he was an adult. He graduated from City College in 1902 and after working in Connecticut as a carpenter, house painter, and teacher, he returned to New York in 1905 to work on the SLP publications Daily People and Weekly People as a reporter, re-write man, and assistant editor. He translated "The Sword of Honor, or the Foundation of the French Revolution" by Eugene Sue and "Patriotism and the Worker" by Gustave Herve for publication by the SLP publishing house, New York Labor News Company. De Leon received an MA in economics from Columbia University in 1912 and a social work degree from the New School of Social Work (then the New York School of Philanthropy) in 1913. He was employed by the American Association for Labor Legislation as a field investigator, writer, and researcher, 1912-1920, while continuing to contribute to SLP publications under the pseudonym, Braset Marteau, but became politically and personally estranged from his father and from the SLP and was expelled from the Party in 1918.
He was briefly a member of the Socialist Party of America, joining the Workers' Council group that became part of the Communist party in 1920. De Leon contributed to and helped to edit the Advance, the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America's newspaper, 1919-1922; was director of the labor research department, Rand School of Social Science, during the 1920s, and edited the American Labor Year Book published by the Rand School. During the 1930s, he taught science and shop at the Walden School, a private progressive school in New York; was a nature and shop counselor at children's summer camps, and, as Bert Grant, wrote a science and nature column for the New Pioneer. From 1943 to 1964 De Leon was assistant research director for the National Maritime Union. He was also active in the Labor Research Association during the 1960s, and was a regular contributor of articles and book reviews to its publication Economic Notes. De Leon was a librarian and French instructor at Kettrell Junior College, a Black college in North Carolina from 1965 to 1967, and died in Ellenville, N.Y., on December 3, 1975.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains correspondence, essays, and fragmentary writings, both handwritten and typed, many touching upon union organization, and the politics and ideology of the American Left. Of special interest is his correspondence (between 1912 and 1914) with Daniel De Leon, Arnold Petersen, and other members of the Socialist Labor Party that capture the ideological conflicts that eventually led to De Leon's estrangement from his father and the Party. Correspondence from 1956-1965 between De Leon and League for Industrial Democracy members including Sidney Henchberg, Harry Laidler, Andrew Shiffrin, and Norman Thomas reflects De Leon's disenchantment with the League's lack of organizational activism. Bitter correspondence from 1964-1965 between De Leon and the president's office of The National Marine Union concerns the abolition of De Leon's position of assistant research director.
Printed materials include flyers, brochures, pamphlets, and arbitration briefs from various labor unions and political organizations, as well as syllabi for courses taught by De Leon and fellow socialists for workers. There is a great deal of material of a personal nature also contained in the collection, consisting of personal and collected poetry, political drama, a scrapbook, a postcard collection, and several job applications for research and civil service work. In addition, materials with references to De Leon consisting of newspaper clippings from The Daily and Weekly People, a political essay, and correspondence between De Leon and members of the Socialist Labor Party and one of its principal leaders, his father Daniel De Leon, have been taken from the Nelson Frank collection and added as an addendum.
An additional box of materials was added to the collection in 2015. These documents consist of correspondence and papers predominantly related to Solon De Leon's participation in labor organizing and education between 1920 and 1980. They also include a number of teaching materials for De Leon's courses in labor research and manuscripts for labor related plays and sketches.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically within each series. Series 8 was added to the colleciton in 2015. These materials have not been arranged by an archivist.
Organized into 8 series:
Missing Title
Research and Writings
Unions
Workers' Education
Political Organizations
Applications
Personal
Addendum
2015 Accretion
Labor unions -- Organizing -- United States.; Labor laws and legislation -- United States.; Typescripts.; Socialists -- United States.; Syllabi.; Daily people; American labor year book; New pioneer (New York, N.Y.); Weekly people; Briefs (legal documents); Teachers |z New York (State) |z New York.; Labor leaders -- United States.; Collective bargaining -- United States.; Labor literature |z United States.; Journalists |z New York (State) |z New York.; Working class |x Education |z United States.; Educators |z United States.; Editors |z New York (State) |z New York.; Correspondence.; Camp counselors |z New York (State); American labor who's who; Essays.; Job applications.; Pamphlets.; Postcards.; Scrapbooks.; National Maritime Union of America. Education Department; Rand School of Social Science. Department of Labor Research; Schiffrin, André; Walden School (New York, N.Y.); Manumit School (Pawling, N.Y.); Socialist Labor Party; League for Industrial Democracy; Socialist Party (U.S.); Petersen, Arnold, 1885-1976; Laidler, Harry W. (Harry Wellington), 1884-1970; American Association for Labor Legislation; Kittrell Junior College; Labor Research Association (U.S.); Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968; Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America; De Leon, Daniel, 1852-1914; Henchberg, Sidney; Gottesman, Ruth De Leon
- Series 1: Research and Writings
  Scope and Content Note
  Research and Writings, consists of a potpourri of personal essays, book reviews, research inquiries, and speeches that span nearly a fifty year period. Of perhaps the most interest is De Leon's 1974 credo of atheism; his 1925 one act musical drama presented at The League for Industrial Democracy conference; his book review of Robert Hoxie's Trade Unionism in the United States (undated); and his 1926 speech to The League for Industrial Democracy entitled "Communism in the USA."
  - Aristotle and Slavery (6p.), undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Book Reviews, undated, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Drama: "Brains" (by De Leon and Wood), "Mechanization Dialogue" (Anonymous), 1925, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Elementary Socialism: Suggested 12-Session Course, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Essays: "My Credo," "March in Proletarian History", 1974, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Historical Development of Socialism, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter to the Editor of World of Tomorrow, Dec 1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Marx, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Outline: Labor Fact Book #13, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Reform, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Report to the N.E.C. [SLP] on Party Press and Literature, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Research: Literary Inquiries on Lincoln Labor Quotes, 1946, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Scrapbook: Solon De Leon Typescripts (subdivided alphabetically by title), undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Speech to League for Industrial Democracy: "Communism in the USA", 1926 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Test: Test and Essay (fragment), 1932 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Value of Labor Legislation and Karl Marx's Attitude Toward It, May 1913 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Series 2: Unions
  Unions, consists of both printed and nonprinted materials including resolutions, organizational histories, pamphlets, newspaper clippings, flyers, meeting notices, and arbitration briefs from theBakery and Confectionery Workers, The National Marine Union, and The United Office and Professional Workers. Also included is correspondence from. 1943 1944 between De Leon and various union officials concerning exhibits and arbitration briefs, and bitter correspondence from 1964 1965 between De Leon and the president's office of The National Marine Union concerning the abolition of De Leon's position of assistant research director of that organization.
  - Bakery and Confectionery Workers: Printed materials and newspaper clippings, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bakery and Confectionery Workers: Resolution on the elimination of night work, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence: Union officials to De Leon, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - National Marine Union: Correspondence to and from De Leon concerning the abolition of his position, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - National Maritime Union: Printed materials, 1953-1954, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - National Maritime Union: Procedure on Financial Reports on Companies, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Report: "Me and The National Marine Union," De Leon, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Pension Certificate, Local 153, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - United Office and Professional Workers (Arbitration Brief by Solon De Leon), Sep 1942 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - United Office and Professional Workers (Arbitration Brief no author), Jan 1944 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - United Office and Professional Workers: The Place of the Industrial Insurance Agents Union in the Recent Improvements in Industrial Insurance (Arbitration Brief prepared by De Leon), Jan 1943 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Series 3: Workers' Education
  Workers' Education, consists of course syllabi from Margaret Daniels, Solon De Leon, David Saposs, and A.L. Wilbert for courses taught to workers in conjunction with The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union and The Jefferson School of Social Science. Also included is an outline by Martin Beardslee of John Cannon's History of Labor in the United States and a lecture by De Leon for The United Labor Education Committee.
  - Beardslee, Martin: Outline of John R. Commons' History of Labor in the United States, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Daniels, Margaret: Syllabus for course on Industrial and Trade Union History of the United States, International Ladies' Garment Workers Union, 1922-1923 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - De Leon, Solon: outline of talk for United Labor Education Committee, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - De Leon, Solon: Syllabi for course of Applied Economics, International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, 1921-1923 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - De Leon, Solon: Syllabus and attendance roll for course on Methods of Labor Research, Jefferson School of Social Science, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - De Leon, Solon: Course syllabi for courses on Labor Legislation, Trade Unionism, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Saposs, David: Syllabus for course on Trade Union Policies and Tactics, International Ladies' Garment Workers Union, 1922-1923 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Wilbert, A.L.: Syllabus for course on modern Economics and Institutions, International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, 1920-1921 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Series 4: Political Organizations
  Political Organizations, consists of printed materials from The League for Industrial Democracy and The Southern Conference Education Fund. The League for Industrial Democracy materials consist of form letters, ballots, flyers, reports, and pamphlets from 1955 1958, while The Southern Conference Educational Fund materials consist of speech transcripts, form letters, minority caucus resolutions, policy committee report positions, and a newspaper (the Southern Patriot) from the years 1973 1975 that chronicle internal political disputes over party ideology and strategy. Also included is correspondence from 1956 1965 between De Leon and League for Industrial Democracy members including Sidney Henchberg, Harry Laidler, Andre Shifften, and Norman Thomas that focus upon De Leon's disenchantment with the League's lack of organizational activism as well as a 1974 letter to Ann Braden and Penny Lane of The Southern Conference Education Fund.
  - League for Industrial Democracy: Correspondence to and from De Leon, 1956-1958, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - League for Industrial Democracy: Printed material, 1955-1958, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Southern Conference Education Fund: letter from De Leon to Lane and Braden, Sep 1974 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Southern Conference Education Fund: Printed material, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Series 5: Applications
  Applications, consists of college transcripts from Columbia and The City College of New York, inquiries, correspondence, and application forms, both Empty and filled out, for teaching, labor research work, and federal civil servant positions. Also included are letters of recommendation and personal resumes.
  - Applications: Inquiries for research and teaching, includes correspondence to and from De Leon, 1931-1932, 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Applications: Civil Service positions, includes letters to and from De Leon, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - College Transcripts: City College of New York, Columbia University, 1932, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Letters of Recommendation, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Resumes, 1943, 1945, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Series 6: Personal
  Personal, consists of a collection of poetry of aesthetic and political orientation, either typewritten or clipped from newspapers and magazines, including a few works of poetry by De Leon himself; and an informal scrapbook that contains clippings on humorous subjects.
  - Manumit School, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Memorabilia: Bookplates (Daniel De Leon), Membership Cards, Seals, 1901-1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Poetry: Personal Poems, undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Poetry: General, 1910-1928 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Scrapbook, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Walden School, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Series 7: Addendum
  Addendum, consists almost exclusively of letters sent and received by De Leon concerning specific ideological and party procedure disputes with the Socialist Labor Party in the form of typewritten and handwritten correspondence as well as letters clipped from the letters to the editor column of The Daily People and Weekly People. Correspondents include such party notables as Daniel De Leon and Arnold Petersen. Also included is a political allegory of the class struggle written by Solon De Leon and entitled "Step At A Time And Something Now."
  - Clippings from Daily People and Weekly People concerning the minutes of the SLP with reference to De Leon, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Correspondence: Solon De Leon to Daniel De Leon, 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Correspondence: Solon De Leon to "Helena", Jun 20, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 51A)
  - Correspondence: Solon De Leon to SLP leadership (Petersen, et al), 1912 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Correspondence: Solon De Leon to SLP leadership (Petersen, et al), 1913 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Correspondence: Solon De Leon to SLP leadership (Petersen, et al), 1914 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Essay: "Step-At-A-Time And Something Now,", ca.1913 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Johnson, Oakley C.: Correspondence re Carl Reeve's The Life and Times of Daniel De Leon (1972), 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Writings By and About Daniel De Leon: a Bibliography / Oakley C. Johnson & Carl Reeve (26 pp), 1966 (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Series 8: 2015 Accretion, 1920-1980; 2014.152 (Box 2)
  This series contains additional correspondence and papers related to Solon De Leon's involvement in labor organizing and education. Correspondence ranges from personal letters from friends spanning several decades to more formal correspondence with organizations with which De Leon was affiliated, including the Rand School of Social Science, League for Industrial Democracy, and the Socialist Labor Party. These records also contains a number of teaching materials related to classes De Leon taught to union workers. These materials also contain some of De Leon's personal writing including plays, sketches, and short stories. It also contains a number of biographical materials related to his father Daniel De Leon.